Finding aid to Klemens von Klemperer papers CA.MS.01117
Smith College Archives
Klemens von Klemperer Papers
1931-1994
Smith College Archives
von Klemperer, Klemens
CA.MS.01117
1.75 linear feet (1 record carton, 1 legal document box)
Klemens von Klemperer was a professor of German History at Smith College from 1949 to 1987. He was a prolific author, publishing eight books and many historical articles. Most of his work concerned German resistance to Hitler during the Nazi regime. He married Smith alumna Elizabeth Gallaher, who taught as a professor of English literature at Smith College. Collection consists of Klemperer's personal correspondence, including letters from family, friends, and colleagues. The bulk of the materials are dated 1935-1965. Most of the letters are written in English, with some in German and French.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Chia Collins, 2018.
Biographical note
Klemens von Klemperer was a professor of German History at Smtih College from 1949 to 1987. He was a prolific author, publishing eight books and many historical articles. Most of his work concerned German resistance to Hitler during the Nazi regime. He married Smith alumna Elizabeth Gallaher, who taught as a professor of English literature at Smith College.
Born in Berlin on November 2, 1916, Klemperer was an anti-Nazi activist as a student in Vienna before the rising political tension as well as his family's Jewish background made him flee to the United States in 1938. Upon arriving in the United States, Klemperer pursued his doctorate at Harvard University, where he stayed at Eliot House. His education was interrupted from 1942-1946 when he served as an intelligence officer for the Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force (SHAEF), the headquarters of the Allied forces in northwest Europe. Klemperer returned to Hardvard in 1946 and received his doctorate in history in 1949.
Klemperer was offered a teaching position at Smith College that same year and went on to teach for thirty seven years. Although he retired officially in 1987, Klemperer continued to work in academia, publishing his most acclaimed book in 1992: German Resistance Against Hitler: the Search for Allies Abroad, 1938-1945>.
Klemperer died on December 23, 2012 at his home in Easthampton. His wife Elizabeth would survive him for three years before her death in 2015.
Related Materials
This collection has material related to the Parker-McCollester Family papers. See also: Individual faculty papers, Box 1040.2, Department of History papers, Box 1165.
Scope and Content
Personal correspondence of Klemens von Klemperer, Smith College Professor of history. Includes letters from family, friends, and colleagues. Some letters are between his wife Elizabeth Gallaher Klemperer and others, including himself. Letters span from Klemperer's time in the United States military, his studies at Eliot House at Harvard University, his appointment to Smith College, and his successive tenure at Smith College. Materials also include several account books, address books, calendars, and diaries, as well as photographs and postcards. The bulk of the materials are dated 1935-1965. Most of the letters are written in English, with some in German and French.
Photographs.; von Klemperer, Elizabeth Gallaher; von Klemperer, Klemens; Chia Collins; von Klemperer, Elizabeth Gallaher; Chia Collins
- Personal correspondence, 1931-1994; 2018-A-0075 (Box 1)
  - "Letters in 1938", 1932-1938 (Box 1)
  - "K - Lily", 1931-1935, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - "Letters in Fall '43 - Spr. '44", 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - "Letter Diary 1943-1944" (Box 1)
  - "Correspondence Out War Years 1943/6", 1943-1946 (Box 1)
  - "Cape Cod 1948" (Box 1)
  - German conference papers: correspondence, itineraries, receipts, 1962 (Box 1)
- Address books, notebooks, and calendars, 1932-1943; 2018-A-0075 (Box 2)
  - "MISC" notebooks, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1945-1946; 2018-A-0075 (Box 2)
  - "Fürsthagen '45/'46", 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - "1945 Paris / Frankfurt" negatives (Box 2)
- Postcards, 1940-1949; 2018-A-0075 (Box 2)